Stop. I am…
‪快住手 我是…
No!
‪不可以！
If he so much as moves his hand,
‪这个人的手只要稍有动作
bring me his head in an instant.
‪你就立刻当场砍下他的人头
Are you just getting home?
‪你现在才回来啊？
Yes, Father.
‪是的
Would you care…
‪要来…
for a duel?
‪比试一场吗？
This is a first.
‪这似乎是我第一次
We never had the opportunity to enjoy drinks together.
‪和你相对而坐一同饮酒
Your swordsmanship has improved.
‪你的剑术实力进步许多
Have you been honing your skills?
‪你有持续在精进吗？
While traveling in Ming,
‪在明国流浪时
I needed to be able to defend myself.
‪我得有足够的底子来自保
It brings me back to the day when you first wanted lessons.
‪我想起你初次提出 ‪要学习剑术的那一天
You said you met someone you wished to protect.
‪你当时说你有个想保护的人对吧？
Was Dam-i her name?
‪是名叫垣的女孩吗？
Were you able to meet her when you returned?
‪你回来后有见到她吗？
They say she died.
‪听说她已香消玉殒
Around that time,
‪那时
she left the palace due to an illness.
‪她因病出宫了
Unaware of that fact, I suspected you.
‪我不晓得缘由 还怀疑了爹
I thought
‪我心想
that you had something to do with…
‪她的消失是否
her disappearance.
‪与爹有关
No!
‪不可以！
Do you still resent me?
‪你还是很埋怨我吗？
It would be a lie to say that I do not.
‪若我否认 那便是谎言
However…
‪然而…
I have been trying to understand you.
‪我正努力去理解
How you stated that you had to make that choice
‪你为了家人不得不走上那条路的
for your family.
‪那番话
Although…
‪那对我而言
your choice still perplexes me.
‪依然难以理解
EPISODE 15
‪第 15 集
-Your Majesty!
‪-殿下！
Your Majesty!
‪殿下！
May I ask who you are?
‪你是哪位？
Please.
‪请饶命
Please spare me.
‪求你饶我一命
So you witnessed my husband's last moments.
‪你见到了我夫君临终的样子吗？
Someone murdered him.
‪他被人所杀害
Murder? What do you mean?
‪杀害？那是什么意思？
Why did my presence make you fear for your life?
‪你为何一见到我就求饶？
I thought Lord Sangheon had sent you.
‪我以为你是尚宪君派来的人
My husband put me in hiding here before he passed away.
‪我夫君在死前将我藏在这个地方
He said there was a chance that Lord Sangheon would send someone.
‪他说尚宪君有可能会派人来家里
Could you inform me of his involvement with Lord Sangheon?
‪你可以告诉我 ‪他与尚宪君间有何渊源吗？
To save my life ten years ago,
‪十年前我夫君为了救我一命
he asked Lord Sangheon for a favor.
‪曾对尚宪君欠下一个莫大的人情
In return, he delivered a letter to someone.
‪其代价就是转交书信给某个人
The man who received it…
‪一收到我夫君转交的书信
was executed for committing treason.
‪那个人就被冠上谋反罪名而丧命
Lord Sangheon has been holding that against my husband
‪他因为那件事被尚宪君逮住了把柄
all this time.
‪直至今日
You should just kill me…
‪请杀了我吧
for this is all my fault.
‪一切都是因我而起
Just to save my worthless life, my husband…
‪为了救我这条贱命 我夫君…
Was the recipient of that letter
‪收到那封信的
the Crown Prince's royal preceptor,
‪是曾为世孙师长的翊善
Kang Hwa-gil?
‪姜澕佶吗？
Listen.
‪今天你对我说的这些
What on earth are you doing?
‪你在做什么？
Oh. It is nothing.
‪没有 没什么
Scribe Jung, here is this month's schedule.
‪注书大人 这是本月的轮值表
Right. Thank you.
‪好 谢谢你
Hold on.
‪等等 那个
It looks like I have been excluded from duties at His Majesty's office.
‪便殿轮值是将我全数排除在外吗？
But that is what you requested.
‪这都是应大人的要求啊
You wished not to be in His Majesty's presence.
‪你希望能尽量减少与殿下碰面的机会
The Chief Royal Secretary saw to it that your request was granted.
‪因此都承旨令监特别宽待你
I am humbled, Chief Royal Secretary.
‪感谢你 都承旨大人
However, I believe I have been burdening Scribe Kim with extra chores.
‪不过这段日子因为我的缘故
I know it was I who requested it,
‪虽然我提出了这种请求
but the guilt has been eating away at me.
‪但心里总觉得过意不去
So from now on, I will take on Scribe Kim's duties as well.
‪从现在起 ‪我会揽下金注书的工作量加倍努力
As of this moment, all entries for the Diaries of the Royal Secretariat
‪政院日记往后都由我全权负责
will be mine to write.
‪来记载
I've been waiting
‪您的这句话
for you to say that.
‪我等了很久
Had you taken any longer…
‪若是再迟一些…
Even if you did…
‪我仍然
I would have waited.
‪会继续等待
No matter how long.
‪无论多久我都愿意
Why are you looking at me like that?
‪你为何那样看着我？
Speak up if you wish.
‪有什么话就直说吧
Well, it is not worth saying.
‪不用了 没什么好说的
Scribe Jung must not have a lot to do
‪郑注书似乎闲来无事
considering how he had the time to place lanterns along the path.
‪领着国家俸禄却忙着点灯
That is because the assigned eunuchs have not done their job properly.
‪那还不是因为尚烛内官并未恪守本分
The path I take is barely lit,
‪居然连寡人要走的路都没点灯
but there are more than enough lanterns near the court conference room.
‪宾厅那边却是灯火通明 亮得刺眼
That is because it is where Lord Sangheon frequents.
‪那是因为尚宪君时常出入宾厅
You know I have very little authority, Your Majesty.
‪小的又没有什么权力 殿下
Scribe Jung, what brings you here?
‪郑注书来便殿有何贵干？
Why you are surprised is beyond me. I am here to fulfill my duties.
‪这还用说？当然是尽注书的本分啊
Writing about His Majesty's daily life
‪将殿下的一言一行 ‪钜细靡遗地记载下来
is my duty as a scribe.
‪就是我这个注书的职责
Is something wrong?
‪为何那样看着我？
Please be at ease and be as you were.
‪自在一点
I will go manage the eunuchs now, Your Majesty.
‪小的去训诫尚烛内官了 殿下
I'll make sure they learn their lesson.
‪得给他们一点颜色瞧瞧才行
Are you sure all went well with His Majesty that night?
‪合房之夜真的没发生什么事吗？
You have been barely eating since.
‪您从那天起就这样食不下咽
Am I that ugly?
‪我就这么丑吗？
Pardon?
‪什么？
What on earth did I do wrong?
‪我到底是哪里冒犯了殿下？
You can have this, Yu-gong.
‪这给你吃吧 俞恭
I do not wish to raise concern by dismissing food all the time.
‪我不想在每次饭菜端上桌时 ‪都说出这种话
Actually, I hear that His Majesty
‪其实小的听说 ‪殿下与其外祖父尚宪君大监
Rather than it being your fault,
‪所以与其说是娘娘冒犯了殿下
it could be that he is keeping his distance
‪更有可能是府院君 ‪集尚宪君的宠爱于一身
since your father is someone who Lord Sangheon trusts.
‪才让殿下基于这个缘故跟您保持距离
It is my father he dislikes, not me?
‪所以他讨厌的不是我 而是我爹？
Forgive me, Your Highness.
‪小的惶恐 娘娘
I just did not want you to blame yourself.
‪小的只是因为娘娘相当自责…
That means he might change his mind depending on what I do.
‪那表示只要我努力 ‪就有可能让他改变心意
Pardon?
‪什么？
Thank you, Yu-gong!
‪谢谢你 俞恭
Who watches over this nation? The Han Family or the Yi Family?
‪这个国家的至尊 ‪究竟是韩氏还是李氏？
Dismiss Lord Sangheon from his position
‪请罢黜阻断言路、垄断国政的尚宪君
-Dismiss Lord Sangheon!
‪-请罢黜尚宪君 殿下！
Dismiss Lord Sangheon, Your Majesty.
‪请罢黜尚宪君 殿下！
-Dismiss Lord Sangheon!
‪-请罢黜尚宪君 殿下！
Dismiss Lord Sangheon, Your Majesty.
‪请罢黜尚宪君 殿下！
-Your Majesty! -Dismiss Lord Sangheon!
‪-殿下！ ‪-请罢黜尚宪君！
For some reason,
‪不知为何
imprisoning them only seems to be a temporary fix.
‪无论鞭打他们或关入大牢 ‪都只能让情况暂时消停
They just keep coming back.
‪他们还是会不停聚集示威
I doubt they will give up any time soon,
‪这样下去似乎不会有罢手的一天
so what should we do, Lord Sangheon?
‪这该如何是好呢？大监
When a dog barks after seeing something,
‪当一只狗看到幻影开始吠叫
other dogs follow despite not seeing it for themselves.
‪就会让一百只狗信以为真而一同吠叫
The scholars outside are only following someone's lead
‪宫外的儒生们只是跟随着某人
and are repeating the same words over and over again.
‪如鹦鹉般不断重复着相同的字句罢了
It…
‪寡人
does not bother me.
‪毫不在意
However…
‪然而
even feathers can sink a ship if there are enough of them.
‪羽毛数量过多也会导致船只沉没
If the number of scholars gathering gradually increases,
‪他们不断地聚集示威
they might become a burden to you.
‪寡人忧心也许会造成
That is what I worry about.
‪外祖父的负担
That being said…
‪所以
May I suggest that we reinstate Lord Shin Yeong-su
‪重新找辛莹秀大监回宫效力
back at the palace?
‪您觉得如何？
Shin Yeong-su who was stripped of his rank and retired to the countryside?
‪您是指遭到免职返乡的辛莹秀吗？
I hear that he has become a mentor to scholars.
‪寡人耳闻他下乡后在教导儒生们
Many look up to him
‪他在儒生当中德望甚高
which is why he could help resolve the issue at hand.
‪或许能对此事有所助益
You are not wrong,
‪殿下之言固然有理
but he does not care about state affairs anymore.
‪但他对朝政毫无大志
A man who was forced to leave
‪被驱逐返乡的人
would have no interest in coming back to the palace.
‪应该绝无回宫的意愿
Good.
‪很好
It means, "Even though no one acknowledges your choices,
‪即便他人不了解
if you are able to always take the path that is right,
‪只要自己能始终如一地 ‪走在正确的道路上
you may also consider yourself to be virtuous."
‪此举即为君子
Have a good day.
‪回去吧
-Thank you, Master.
‪-是 老师
My lord!
‪大监大人
You have a visitor from Hanyang.
‪你有来自汉阳的访客
-Hanyang? -Yes, my lord.
‪-汉阳？ ‪-是的
Goodness, you've learned quite a lot.
‪唉唷 你学习的进度很快呢
All right. Keep up the good work.
‪唉唷 认真学习啊
My goodness.
‪唉唷
It sure has been a while, Master Yeosan.
‪唉唷 我们多久没见了啊？闾山先生
But the weight of my sin still remains heavy.
‪我的罪过依旧深重
I could not possibly return to a place within the palace.
‪这样我岂敢重返仕途呢？
Come on. Must you relentlessly decline?
‪唉唷 你先别一口回绝嘛
Maybe you could help me save face.
‪至少看在我的面子上啊
If I return empty-handed,
‪若我远道而来却空手而回
it would leave me in a predicament at the palace.
‪可是会十分难堪的
Besides…
‪况且…
I come bearing a royal order from His Majesty himself.
‪我甚至专程 ‪把殿下颁布的教旨送过来了
And that would mean it comes from the Chief State Councilor.
‪这不是殿下 而是领相的意思吧
I have voiced my opinion.
‪我已经表明我的意愿了
Please let the Chief State Councilor know.
‪请代为转达给领相
Please, Lord Shin.
‪等等 大监
I have relayed the order, so deliver the refusal yourself.
‪我已经转交给你了 ‪若要婉拒请你自己出面
Wait. Hold on.
‪等等 这个…
Let's go!
‪走吧！
BULBIBULMYEONG
‪（不飞不鸣）
If a boat filled with passengers were to tilt to one side,
‪当载满乘客的船只倾向其中一侧时
who do you think would fall into the water first?
‪你认为谁会先掉入水中？
The first to be thrown overboard will be the people who have no power or wealth.
‪率先牺牲的绝对是 ‪毫无权势又一无所有的百姓
That is why…
‪因此
I stand here asking you…
‪寡人希望你能稳住重心
to keep the boat well-balanced.
‪不让这艘船沉没
BULBIBULMYEONG
‪（不飞不鸣）
Shin Yeong-su is hereby appointed
‪“辛莹秀
as Inspector General of the Office of the Inspector General.
‪被任命为司宪府大司宪
Do not take your responsibilities lightly,
‪其责任重大
reproach and rectify any wrongdoings,
‪应弹劾施政 监督百官
and supervise the officials into seeking the right path.
‪引领众人走向正确的道路”
I am humbled by your boundless generosity, Your Majesty.
‪圣恩浩荡 殿下
I did not think you would actually return.
‪我没料到你真的会回来
Ignoring the summons from one's monarch
‪对国家的召唤视而不见
would also be an act of defiance.
‪并非为臣之道
What happened is in the past now,
‪往事就一笔勾销吧
so I hope we get along, Inspector General.
‪往后还请你多加指教 大司宪令监
Of course.
‪是
Will this not have any repercussions?
‪这样不要紧吗？
The Inspector General
‪位居大司宪的话
could surely get in the way of your political endeavors.
‪将足以成为大监仕途上的绊脚石
I can always utilize him to my advantage
‪必要之时善加利用后
and have him serve a purpose.
‪让他达成我的目的就行了
The bird that stays grounded in silence.
‪既不飞又不啼叫的蜷缩之鸟
Am I to believe it refers to Your Majesty?
‪指的就是殿下吗？
I take it that the Chief Royal Secretary safely delivered my message.
‪看来都承旨顺利传达了寡人的旨意
Then can I believe what I assumed is correct?
‪那臣所解释的意涵是否也正确呢？
Probably.
‪或许吧
HIS MAJESTY MEETS WITH THE INSPECTOR GENERAL
‪（上入在便殿 ‪召见任职大司宪辛莹秀）
Forgive me for saying this,
‪恕臣直言
but I do not intend to be a piece in your political games, Your Majesty.
‪臣并不想替殿下的政治效劳
It means that I will not always blindly stand beside you.
‪这意味着臣不会 ‪总是与殿下站在同一阵线
If you take the wrong path,
‪若殿下误入歧途
I will be the first to go in the opposite direction.
‪臣将率先步上与其相悖的方向
Will that be acceptable?
‪即便如此也无妨吗？
Of course.
‪那是当然
It is for that reason that I requested your reinstatement.
‪那就是寡人将你重新召回的理由
To rectify and reform the court
‪为了让我外祖父所掌控的这个朝廷
that is in my grandfather's grasp.
‪回到应有的轨道上
DAILY LOG OF CARGO SHIPS
‪（《漕运船日志》）
This proves the Minister of Taxation's illegal activities.
‪这本账簿记载着户曹判书的贪污事由
It will be the first matter you investigate as Inspector General.
‪这将会成为大司宪
Scribe Jung.
‪郑注书
What you just heard--
‪方才那些对谈内容…
Fret not, Your Majesty,
‪您无须担心
for I left it all out.
‪我没有记载下来
It describes a bird
‪这是描述一只在三年内既不啼叫
that stays grounded for three years in silence.
‪也不飞翔的鸟对吧？
To make up for the time it had to stay huddled,
‪在按捺多时后一旦展翅高飞
it soars up above the clouds.
‪便会一飞冲天
And when it cries,
‪一旦开始啼叫
it sends shocks across the lands.
‪便会震动天地
You have waited for the right time to achieve something great.
‪您为了成就大事而在等待时机吗？
If you would allow it, I would like to join you.
‪那也让臣一同加入吧
But this is my burden to bear…
‪这是我分内的事
and it entails risks.
‪而且又充满危险
Remember that day in the woods?
‪那天在那片树林里
Everything we talked about that day
‪我们当时许下的承诺
can no longer be promised.
‪现在已无法兑现了 不是吗？
So please…
‪因此
allow me to at least be by your side in this way.
‪即便是这种方式 ‪也让我守在您的身边吧
We are now in the same boat,
‪现在我都成了您的共犯
so you cannot ignore my situation.
‪您还要继续视而不见吗？
Then, promise me this one thing.
‪那答应我一件事
When I tell you to stop,
‪当我要你停下来的时候
you must.
‪你一定要照做
I order you as the King.
‪这是王命
Then I will oblige, Your Majesty.
‪我会的 殿下
Minister of Taxation Park Won-hyeong purposely unloaded rice meant for the army
‪户曹判书朴元亨
Head to where the ships bound for Hamgil Province are docked
‪你们至开往咸吉道的码头
and raid the storage facility frequently used by his people.
‪突袭户判的人常用的仓库
You will find the missing rice.
‪那里会有被侵吞的军粮米
Also, the Minister of Taxation disobeyed the law
‪此外 户曹判书还会收买船夫
by bribing crewmen to deliberately wreck the ship.
‪-打开 ‪-故意破坏船只 其罪重大
He must be captured and brought to justice.
‪立即逮捕他 将他绳之以法
Do you understand?
‪明白了吗？
Search every corner!
‪仔细地搜！
-Yes, Inspector!
‪-是！
-Goodness, what is the meaning of this? -Oh, dear.
‪-唉唷 这是怎么回事？ ‪-唉唷
My goodness.
‪我的天啊
Identify yourselves!
‪你们是什么人？
We are from the Office of the Inspector General.
‪我们来自司宪府
What did you say?
‪什么？
Minister Park, you must come with us.
‪户判大监 要请你跟我们走一趟
How dare you!
‪你这是在做什么？
Do you think you can get away
‪你以为这样羞辱我之后
with humiliating me like this?
‪自己能全身而退吗？
The rice meant for soldiers in Hamgil Province
‪应运往咸吉道的军粮米
was stacked in your personal shed.
‪却堆放在户判大监的私人仓库中
That is preposterous. I know nothing about this.
‪那不可能 我不晓得有这回事
This clearly says otherwise.
‪这里有确凿的证据
DAILY LOG OF CARGO SHIPS
‪（《漕运船日志》）
This ledger has records of you utilizing the cargo ship for personal use.
‪这本账簿里有着漕运船 ‪作为私用的记录
Well, that…
‪那是…
The people have been making clothes out of hay to stay covered
‪百姓衣衫褴褛、饥饿难耐
and eating bark from trees
‪需编织稻秆蔽体
just to appease their hunger,
‪用树皮来充饥果腹
but the Minister of Taxation
‪你身为户曹判书
has been stealing from the nation to feed his own belly.
‪却用国家的财产来中饱私囊
Your Majesty.
‪殿下
I hear you have been using cargo ships for personal matters.
‪寡人耳闻你将漕运船作为私用
You also hoarded the rice meant for our soldiers.
‪除此之外 还侵吞了士兵们的食粮
I doubt that even you will question my decision to behead you.
‪就算即刻斩首 你也无话可说吧
All I did
‪臣只是
was aid Lord Sangheon.
‪助尚宪君大监一臂之力罢了
I had no other intention, Your Majesty.
‪绝对没有其他意图
I see.
‪这样啊
So you were following my grandfather's orders?
‪所以这是我外祖父的命令？
Pardon?
‪什么？
This is why one must never trust another human being.
‪所以才说不该对人太好 ‪免得日后遭到背叛
After all the trust
‪我外祖父
my grandfather put in you?
‪似乎相当看重你 户判
He will truly be disappointed to hear that you pointed to him
‪倘若他得知你供称他是背后主谋
as the mastermind.
‪肯定会大失所望
It was a slip of tongue.
‪是臣失言了
I am the one who--
‪这全是臣独自…
You will take all the blame instead?
‪你想独自揽下罪名？
Well, that is…
‪那个…
Please have mercy on me, Your Majesty!
‪请您饶命 殿下！
Allow me to present an option.
‪寡人给你一条生路
Leave the palace as ordered
‪安静地遵照处分离宫的话
and I will keep quiet about you betraying my grandfather.
‪我就绝口不提你背叛我外祖父一事
You are probably well aware of this,
‪户判想必也很清楚
but my grandfather is a ruthless man.
‪我外祖父毫无怜悯之心
Rather than receiving punishment from him,
‪与其听由他处罚 为此付出代价
this will surely be in your favor.
‪我的处置想必更为人道
I will obey any order you lay upon me,
‪臣将遵从殿下的旨意
You used the cargo ship
‪你利用漕运船
to secretly move weapons to Hamgil Province.
‪偷偷将武器运往咸吉道对吧？
Pardon?
‪什么？
Name the guild that provides my grandfather with the weapons.
‪说出是哪个商团供给武器给我外祖父
Do so, and I will keep my word.
‪那我就会信守承诺 放你一条生路
My lord.
‪大监大人
The Office of the Inspector General raided Minister Park's residence.
‪司宪府突袭了户判大监的私宅
What?
‪什么？
Minister Park must have hoarded the rice that was unloaded
‪户判为了用漕运船运送武器 ‪便侵吞粮食
to make room for the weapons.
‪囤积在私人仓库的样子
Weapons ready to be shipped to Yeoyeon tomorrow are in storage nearby.
‪那附近还保管着一批 ‪明天要运往闾延的武器
If they manage to find it--
‪若司宪府连那个地方都发现的话…
-Burn them all. -Pardon?
‪-全都烧个精光 ‪-什么？
Was I not clear?
‪没听到我说的吗？
Yes, my lord. I will get it done.
‪是 小的遵命
What…
‪您现在
game are you playing?
‪在跟臣玩什么把戏？
The Inspector General uncovered Minister Park's misconduct.
‪大司宪揭露了户判贪污之事
By exploiting the authority you possess,
‪他滥用外祖父的权力
he hoarded rice meant for our army.
‪侵吞军粮米
Have you already forgotten
‪我明明就吩咐您什么都别做
-how I told you not to do anything? -Of course not.
‪您这么快就忘了啊？
But how could I sit idly by
‪他玷污了外祖父的名声
while someone tarnishes your good name?
‪寡人岂能坐视不管？
-It is why-- -Minister Park…
‪-所以… ‪-户判
is one of my people.
‪是我的人
Therefore, I should be the one to punish him.
‪因此即便要处分 也该由我来执行
You have no saying in this matter.
‪殿下没有选择权可言
Grandfather…
‪外祖父
if word gets out about this,
‪当此事公诸于世
we will face the grievance of the people
‪好不容易才稳住的民心
we barely managed to subside.
‪又会产生动摇
But that will not happen
‪那同样也是
as long as you keep your mouth shut.
‪只要殿下守口如瓶便不会发生
Do not dare to challenge me.
‪不要试图挑战我的权威
This will be the last time I look past
‪我对您那天真把戏的容忍
your cheeky antics.
‪也到此为止了
We could pay with our lives if we get caught.
‪像这样偷偷摸摸的 ‪一旦被发现就完蛋了
You are the last person I expected to see here, Section Chief.
‪话说正郎为何又在这凑热闹？
One must solve the problems that one creates.
‪解铃还须系铃人
I am curious though.
‪不过户判大监已被司宪府收押
We are running out of time.
‪没时间了
Please hurry.
‪动作快 快点写吧
Hurry.
‪是
Identify yourselves!
‪是谁在那里？
What are you doing here?
‪你们在这里做什么？
Well…
‪那个…
The alcohol must be getting to me.
‪我醉了
Goodness. I'm seeing things.
‪都出现幻影了 真是
-Goodness. -He's drunk.
‪-唉唷 ‪-他醉了
Minister of Taxation Park Won-hyeong
‪户曹判书朴元亨
has been caught siphoning rice meant for the army
‪侵吞运往咸吉道的军粮米
and storing them for personal gain.
‪中饱私囊之举败露
While trying to cover up his crimes, he also purposely wrecked the ships.
‪此外为了掩盖贪污之实 ‪而蓄意破坏船只
His disrespect for state property
‪犯下恣意破坏国家财产的重罪
is being investigated by the Office of the Inspector General.
‪而受到司宪府的监察
The people have been making clothes out of hay to stay covered
‪百姓衣衫褴褛、饥饿难耐 ‪需编织稻秆蔽体
and eating bark from trees just to appease their hunger,
‪并用树皮充饥果腹
which is why
‪他身为户曹判书
the Minister of Taxation's selfish decision to steal from the state
‪却盗取国家财产中饱私囊
leaves misery in its wake.
‪真令人不胜唏嘘
All those who serve at the royal court
‪朝廷百官理应身先士卒
must request that Minister Park be impeached.
‪奏请弹劾户曹判书朴元亨
You may write this in the diary.
‪在日记上记载
"During the morning assembly,
‪“今日在朝参之上
the Chief State Councilor requested that I dismiss
‪领相奏请弹劾
the Minister of Taxation from office."
‪户曹判书朴元亨”
The 35th stratagem listed in Sonjabyeongbeob.
‪《孙子兵法》第35计
The yeonhwan stratagem.
‪连环计
"Utilize several schemes at once to achieve your goal."
‪“一次运用多项计策来达成目的”
It was a clever one, might I add.
‪真是个绝佳的计策啊 郑注书
Are words all that I receive?
‪只有口头上的称赞吗？
Rather than a compliment in words, I would like a wish to be granted.
‪既然要赞许臣 ‪那就替臣实现一个心愿吧
A wish?
‪心愿？
All right. Let me hear it.
‪好 说来听听
Well, it…
‪那个心愿是…
Before anything…
‪在此之前
you must promise something.
‪您得先答应我一件事
Please promise that you will not be angry.
‪您保证绝对不会生气
What could this wish of yours be?
‪到底是什么心愿？
Fine. Consider the promise made--
‪好 我答应你
What…
‪这…
What on earth are you doing?
‪你这是在做什么？
You promised
‪您答应过我
to never get angry.
‪绝对不会生气
What is it this time?
‪这次又是什么？
It is a report from the Ministry of Rites.
‪这是礼曹要上呈的启本
Please take it to His Majesty.
‪请转交给殿下
Why are you giving this to me when you could deliver it yourself?
‪这种东西为何交给我？ ‪你应该亲自上呈啊
His office is only a few steps away.
‪这里离便殿又不远
I am quite busy these days.
‪我最近比较忙
I thank you in advance.
‪拜托你了
All right.
‪是
What is with him these days? Did he do something to upset His Majesty?
‪他最近怎么老是这样？ ‪是做了什么愧对殿下的事吗？
Just so you know…
‪我啊…
I will not…
‪应该
be leaving the palace.
‪无法离开王宫了
And my feelings cannot be brushed away.
‪而且也无法斩断我的情意
Right. I see.
‪好 这样啊
Consider yourself heard.
‪那我知道你的心意了
Her Majesty the Queen wishes to speak to you both.
‪中殿娘娘想跟两位见个面
So…
‪本宫
I asked to speak to you both
‪之所以会如此失礼地提出
despite it being an inconvenience for you
‪跟两位见面的请求
because you are His Majesty's closest friends
‪是因为两位是殿下最亲近的友人
and are close friends yourselves.
‪又耳闻两位是金兰之交
I hope this doesn't make you uncomfortable.
‪这个场合应该不会让你们 ‪感到不自在吧？
No, of course not.
‪是 当然不会
We did learn from the same mentor as young boys, but…
‪我们仅是自小师承同门 ‪同窗研读的关系
Yes, we have known each other for quite some time.
‪但确实结识已久
May I ask why you summoned us here, Your Highness?
‪不过您找我们过来所为何事？
I was hoping to ease His Majesty's mind from his worries regarding state affairs.
‪本宫想抚慰殿下 ‪忙于繁重政务的疲惫之心
Is there anything in particular that he likes?
‪因此想知道殿下特别喜欢哪些东西
I thought you two would know.
‪总觉得两位应该最清楚
His Majesty sometimes wishes to appease his sweet tooth.
‪殿下偶尔会想吃甜食
Perhaps candy or…
‪像是糖…
Candy?
‪糖？
No, peaches or dried persimmons.
‪像是桃子或柿饼
Peaches?
‪桃子？
His Majesty is fond of flowers,
‪殿下很喜欢花卉
so he would prefer peach blossoms to peaches…
‪因此比起桃子 他更喜爱桃花
and flowers from persimmon trees rather than the actual fruit.
‪而柿子花又比柿饼更深得他的心
His Majesty enjoys going on walks on his own.
‪殿下喜爱独自散步
Rather than walks, he loves to sit in peace
‪比起散步
It shows that he wishes to spend time on his own.
‪因此应该是希望能有独处的时间
PEACE, WIND CHIMES
‪风铃声…
Then what does he dislike?
‪那他讨厌什么呢？
Pardon?
‪什么？
He will probably dislike others talking about him
‪殿下讨厌别人像这样在背后
behind his back like this.
‪恣意谈论他的事
That is true. He will not take it lightly.
‪是的 没错 殿下绝不会轻饶
The fact that we spoke about him--
‪我们恣意说出殿下的事…
We urge you to keep it a secret, Your Highness.
‪请您务必保密 中殿娘娘
Please.
‪一定不能泄漏
He hates when people speak about him behind his back.
‪他不喜欢别人恣意谈论自己的事
I see.
‪好
No wonder you are good friends.
‪两位不愧是莫逆之交
Do not worry.
‪请不用担心
Excuse me.
‪我失陪一下
Please be careful. Let us carry it for you instead.
‪请您小心 让小的来拿吧 好吗？
What on earth is that big lump I see?
‪那一大束是什么东西？
Your Majesty!
‪殿下
It's not even ripe.
‪这还没熟
My Queen, what is all this?
‪中殿 这些是什么？
I brought you some flowers because I heard you like them.
‪臣妾听说殿下喜爱花卉 ‪便带了一些过来
"Some" flowers?
‪一些花？
Thank you.
‪谢谢你
I hear you also have a sweet tooth.
‪而且臣妾也耳闻您喜爱甜食
They will rejuvenate you after grueling hours at the office.
‪在处理政务感到疲惫时食用 ‪能让您提振精神
One only hopes that you are in good health, Your Majesty.
‪恳请您保重龙体 殿下
Join me.
‪跟我携手合作吧
Avenge the late King
‪替先王的枉死复仇
and help build the world your father dreamed of.
‪让你父亲所描绘的世界得以实现
I told you to stop!
‪我不是要你住手吗？
I have failed to protect you too.
‪我也同样保护不了你
What is it that infuriated and saddened you this much?
‪是什么让你那么气愤又哀伤
To the point that you were suffering even in your dream.
‪害你连在梦中都如此痛苦？
It seems your honest heart-to-heart…
‪看来殿下的真心
did not work as intended.
‪并没有得到正确的解读呢
Your Majesty, Officer Yoon has sent word.
‪殿下 副护军捎来口信
Why are you here?
‪你怎么会在这？
I am the assassin who attacked you
‪很久以前在讲武场袭击邸下的刺客
at the royal hunting.
‪就是我
I needed to make room for myself at the palace
‪为了刺杀上王殿下
in order to assassinate the late King.
‪我需要一个潜入东宫的机会
All this time, I have deceived you.
‪这段日子臣欺瞒殿下之罪
And for that, I will gladly accept any punishment.
‪无论您下达何种处分 臣都甘愿承受
I ran into him while tracking the evidence related
‪臣在追查上王殿下被毒害的真相时
to your father's murder.
‪与他携手合作
He…
‪他…
was able to witness the late King's last moments.
‪目击了先王临终的那一刻
You had already left the palace,
‪你既然离宫了
so you could have kept the truth buried.
‪大可选择佯装不知 隐瞒这一切
What is your reason for coming clean?
‪为何现在才回来说出真相？
The late King…
‪先王
shared a piece of this tally with my father.
‪与家父各自持有一半的符节
I wish to carry on their desire.
‪臣想继承他们的遗志
"The last night of the year."
‪“除夕”
He is Kang Eun-seo, the son of Preceptor Kang Hwa-gil.
‪他是翊善姜澕佶之子 姜溵曙
His father was executed after being framed as a traitor
‪他爹惨遭尚宪君诬陷
by Lord Sangheon.
‪背负着逆贼罪名而死
GANGNYEONGJEON
‪（康宁殿）
What is it that you saw?
‪你看到了什么？
Who…
‪是谁
murdered my father?
‪害死我父王的？
I have committed a mortal sin.
‪臣罪该万死 大监
Please find it in you to forgive me this once.
‪请你原谅我这一次吧
To what extent does His Majesty know?
‪殿下知道了哪些事？
Is he also aware of the weapons
‪连要将武器运往闾延的事
set to be shipped to Yeoyeon?
‪他也晓得吗？
Of course not.
‪那怎么可能呢？
All he knows is that I hoarded the rice meant for the soldiers.
‪他只知道我侵吞军粮米
Until I reach out to you,
‪在我找你回来之前
you will remove yourself from the palace.
‪暂且离开王宫吧
Pardon?
‪什么？
I am humbled by your benevolence, Lord Sangheon.
‪谢谢你 大监 真是感激不尽
He is aware of my affairs in Yeoyeon.
‪他知道闾延的事呢
Deal with him accordingly
‪你追上去了结他的性命
so that word does not travel from him.
‪避免他泄漏口风
Is it absolutely necessary to take it that far?
‪你一定得做到那个地步吗？
After making one mistake,
‪曾犯下一个过失的人
it is easy to make another.
‪也会犯下其他过失
It is why I cannot condone
‪因此我连一次失误
even a single mistake.
‪都不允许
Commander Jung, why…
‪内禁卫长 你怎么会…
Come back here!
‪你们这群混账要去哪啊？
Commander Jung.
‪内禁卫长
Father.
‪爹
You're home.
‪你现在才回来啊
Yes, I see you are not in bed yet.
‪是啊 你还没睡啊？
The night air is refreshing.
‪夜晚的空气很清新
I see.
‪这样啊
You do not seem well. Is something troubling you?
‪你的脸色看起来不太好 ‪是发生了什么事吗？
I am tired, that is all.
‪我只是有点累
He must have been exhausted.
‪殿下似乎累坏了
I will stay here,
‪我会守在这里
so excuse yourselves and let His Majesty rest in silence.
‪你们先退下 让殿下好好休息
-Yes, Court Lady Kim.
‪-是 尚宫娘娘
Could there be anything to use as a blanket?
‪没有什么能盖的吗？
Your Majesty?
‪殿下
Your Majesty, where are you?
‪殿下 您在哪里？
His Majesty…
‪我们殿下
is so good-looking.
‪真是英俊
Your Majesty?
‪殿下
Forgive me, Your Majesty.
‪臣妾惶恐 殿下
I was only trying to dust something off your face.
‪您的脸上似乎沾到了什么东西
Were you hurt?
‪你有没有受伤？
No, I am fine.
‪臣妾没事
Let's go. How about we go to my quarters for some tea?
‪我们走
Of course, Your Majesty.
‪好的 殿下
I actually come bearing fragrant tea for you to enjoy.
‪我正好带了香气逼人的茶过来
I will request for it to be served.
‪为了让您品尝才会来此
What are you doing alone behind the tree?
‪你为何独自站在树木后面？
What were you up to?
‪你一个人在这做什么？
Yes?
‪嗯？
Was there a reason the Queen came by?
‪中殿娘娘来此有何贵干？
She just came to see how I was doing.
‪就只是过来问候一下
Oh, I see.
‪这样啊
You must have been very tired.
‪您好像很疲惫
You were dozing off out in the open.
‪居然睡得那么毫无防备
Pardon?
‪什么？
What I am saying is that you did not even have a guard by your side.
‪我是说您身边居然一个护卫都没有
The palace can be such a dangerous place!
‪王宫是个多么危险的地方啊
Forgive me, Your Majesty.
‪臣惶恐
Hold on.
‪莫非
Are you jealous right now?
‪你是在吃醋吗？
Jealous?
‪什么吃醋？
It is only because you could have been in harm's way.
‪我只是担心殿下会有危险
I was worried.
‪只是出于担心
I am right about you being jealous.
‪对吧？你在吃醋
We are in your office.
‪这里是便殿
Whatever you say must go in the diary, so please choose your words carefully.
‪一切都得记载下来 ‪请您留意自身的言行 殿下
Your Majesty, the director of the Office of Royal Decrees
‪殿下 艺文馆大提学
has requested an audience.
‪请求轮对
Let him in.
‪好 让他进来
Why did His Majesty want to see me here?
‪殿下为何突然找我来这？
Your Majesty.
‪殿下
What…
‪殿…
What could this be about?
‪您为何推我？
I would rather you not tease me, Your Majesty.
‪请别再戏弄我了 殿下
Tease you?
‪戏弄？
I am quite serious.
‪这不是啊
Pardon?
‪什么？
I remember what you once told me.
‪郑注书曾说过
That you would endure everything.
‪你会承担一切
I will do the same.
‪我也要来试试
I am ready to bear the consequences of my feelings.
‪试着来承担我的这份情意
Subtitle translation by: Hye-lim Park
‪字幕翻译：钟见悦